Problem: biodiversity evidence is fragmented. Occurrence
records may live in one system, DNA barcode fragments in
another, BLAST or Sequence ID tables in a lab pipeline, and
publication metadata in spreadsheets. When these pieces are
not connected, useful evidence can be lost, and species-level
claims can become stronger than the data actually support.
EcoGenesis is a Barcode-to-GBIF Evidence Compiler. It takes
DNA barcode, metabarcoding, Sequence ID and BLAST-like
outputs, then runs deterministic evidence gates. The result is
not just a label. It is a safe taxonomic rank decision, a
publication-readiness state, a repair plan, and a reproducible
Evidence Pack.
On the public demo site, the interface is organized around the
whole evidence path. Judges can open the overview, run the
compiler, inspect the evidence map, view the fragment graph,
check validation, read methods and download the Evidence Pack.
Each section has its own public route, so the workflow is easy
to review and cite.
The Run Compiler screen is where molecular evidence enters the
system. A user can upload a CSV, start from a demo workflow,
or test a reference fragment. The compiler validates required
molecular fields, sequence context, reference-hit metrics, and
publication metadata before it lets any record move forward.
In the mixed demo, records do not collapse into one simplistic
answer. Some are species-safe, some are genus-safe, some
remain weak, and some are not publishable until metadata are
repaired. This is the core behavior: useful molecular evidence
is preserved, but unsafe species exports and incomplete
publication records are stopped.
The Evidence Map turns the results into a spatial evidence
atlas. It connects GBIF occurrence context with claim states,
snapshot hashes, VSEA rows, graph objects and export
boundaries. The map is not a proof of presence by itself; it
is a way to inspect provenance, context and claim strength in
one place.
In the live Evidence Map, reviewers can see which rows are
safe, repair-required, review-only or blocked. The same view
exposes judge-mode checks, graph audits and export boundaries
before download. That makes the spatial layer explanatory and
auditable rather than a visual shortcut.
The Fragment Graph shows how marker fragments link to
reference taxa and safe LCA decisions. When a fragment points
to multiple close taxa, EcoGenesis reports the most specific
safe rank instead of forcing a species claim. This keeps
evidence, competitors and caveats together.
Uncertainty is handled through explicit gates: identity and
coverage, ambiguity and LCA downgrade, barcode gap, diagnostic
k-mer support, marker profile, publication readiness and graph
provenance. A top hit does not become a species-level output
unless the required gates pass.
Validation is built into the submission package. The project
includes backend tests, frontend tests, competition batches,
adversarial batches, graph audits and contest-readiness
checks. The important validation target is fail-closed
behavior: weak coverage, close competitors, metadata gaps and
unsafe exports must be blocked or downgraded.
The final deliverable is the Evidence Pack. It includes CSV,
JSON, HTML, VSEA, graph and audit outputs for review, repair
and reuse. Researchers can inspect sequence safety tables,
publication blockers, molecular evidence reports, graph
provenance and machine-readable export artifacts.
EcoGenesis is already a working contest prototype with a live
demo, public source code, reproducible outputs and
downloadable evidence artifacts. It can scale to larger
reference libraries, institutional pipelines, richer GBIF
publishing workflows and broader molecular evidence
observatories. The call to action is simple: open the live
demo, run the workflow, and inspect the evidence before
publication.