Workflow scrolls from molecular input to Evidence Pack, map and graph.
Overview states the product claim and exposes the public source repository.
Run Compiler shows input, validation, hard gates, decisions, blockers and repairs.
Evidence Map links GBIF context, claim states, blockers and export boundaries.
Evidence Graph keeps provenance visible and cannot upgrade weak or blocked claims.
Evidence Map exports package VSEA, graph, GBIF preview and AI guardrail files.
Judge view exposes contest readiness, verification reports and adversarial packs.
Fragment Graph checks a marker fragment, hit comparison and safest LCA.
Validation shows batch, adversarial, graph, VSEA and export guardrail checks.
Methods and Audits document gates, failure modes and publication boundaries.
Evidence Pack exports CSV, JSON, HTML, VSEA, graph and audit files for reuse.